<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Horrible newes from Lancashire, declared in a letter sent from Lancaster by one Mr. Benjamin Williamson to Mr. Adam Andrewes merchant and inhabitant in the burrough of Southwarke. Wherein is related what tumnltuous [sic] uprores the papists in those parts have lately made to the terror of the inhabitants of the said county. Also a true relation how the Protestants rose in armes and forced them to flye. Likewise a large manifestation of the great care of the sheriffe of Lancaster to disarme the papists, and to prevent such uprores and tumults. Together with an order sent from the House of Commons to the high sheriffe of Lancaster, touching the suppressing of the abovesaid tumults. Iohn Browne, Cler. Parl.</title>
            <author>Williamson, Benjamin, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E149_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R848</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873322</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 26:E149[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Horrible newes from Lancashire, declared in a letter sent from Lancaster by one Mr. Benjamin Williamson to Mr. Adam Andrewes merchant and inhabitant in the burrough of Southwarke. Wherein is related what tumnltuous [sic] uprores the papists in those parts have lately made to the terror of the inhabitants of the said county. Also a true relation how the Protestants rose in armes and forced them to flye. Likewise a large manifestation of the great care of the sheriffe of Lancaster to disarme the papists, and to prevent such uprores and tumults. Together with an order sent from the House of Commons to the high sheriffe of Lancaster, touching the suppressing of the abovesaid tumults. Iohn Browne, Cler. Parl.</title>
                  <author>Williamson, Benjamin, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1[i.e.8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Horton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642. June 3.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Page 8 misnumbered 1.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Horrible Newes from LANCASHIRE, Declared in a Letter ſent from <hi>Lancaſter</hi> by one Mr. <hi>Benjamin Williamſon</hi> to Mr. <hi>Adam Andrewes</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant and Inhabitant in the Burrough of <hi>Southwarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is related what Tumultuous Vprores the Papiſts in thoſe parts have lately made to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Inhabitants of the ſaid County.</p>
            <p>Alſo a true Relation how the Proteſtants roſe in Armes and forced them to flye.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe a large Manifeſtation of the great care of the Sheriffe of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> to diſarme the Papiſts, and to prevent ſuch Vprores and Tumults.</p>
            <p>Together with an Order ſent from the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to the High Sheriffe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> touching the ſuppreſſing of the aboveſaid Tumults.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Browne, Cler. Parl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>J. Horton,</hi> 1642. <hi>June</hi> 3.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156723:2"/>
            <head>Horrible Newes from <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Troubles and diſtractions of this Kingdome are great and manifold are the plots and deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that the Papiſts have in agitation both againſt the King and Parliament, private intentions, and publique actions, private deſignes, and cunning Stratagems have beene long hatching, and now they ſee ſuch diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſturbances betwixt the King and Parliament, they Preſume to put that in action, which has ſo long beene concealed.</p>
            <p>A large and apparent teſtimony of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156723:3"/>this, late happened in Lancaſhire in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> on the 25. day of <hi>May</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 7. Miles of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> upon a great Plaine, there aſſembled a great number of Papiſts, to the vallew of 3. hundred, with Swords by their ſides, waiting as it ſemes for ſome more Company, what their councells or determination, were is not yet knowne.</p>
            <p>Onely this I am informed, that they affrighted the neighbouring Inhabitants ſo that they gathered together, and put themſelves into a Poſture of defence, in the beſt manner that they could, withall ſending with their beſt ſpeed to the high Sheriffe of the ſaid County to give him information of what they had cauſe to feare, but the high Sheriffe being rode to <hi>Lancaſter</hi> to cauſe the Order of the houſes of Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſuppreſſing ſuch meetings, to be publiſhed, by which meanes they were fruſtrate of their hopes, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156723:3"/>they tooke courage, and with unite conſent march'd out upon them, and by the advice of ſome Gentlemen that were there, ſent Maſſages unto them to demand the cauſe of that aſsembly, it being contrary to the Command of the high Court of Parliament, withall deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to depart by faire meanes, (withall giving them this to boo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, that if they would not by faire meanes they would (knowing it to be for the preſervation of his Maieſty, and the good of the Kingdome, to quell ſuch uprores) force their departure, or make their Place of meeting a <hi>terrene Golgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> and bury them and their deſignes together, which blunt embaſsage af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted ſo the Papiſts, that they begun apace to take their Iourneys each to his habitation, muttering forth words full of deſpight and anger, as that the time ſhould come ere long that they ſhould repent thoſe words, ſpeaking as if they had ſome plot in agitaton.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:156723:4"/>
            <p> This makes the Proteſtants to keepe a wary Watch and looke preciſely on the Catholiques, the high Sheriffe uſing all ſpeedy meanes for to diſarme them and take away their force, hoping by that meanes to hinder any publique outrages, withall promiſing to ſtuddy and conforme themſelves to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the high Court of Parliament, they being the cheife preſervers of the King and Kingdomes peace, whoſe Councells God direct for the beſt, ſo that true Religion may be ſettled, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty increaſed, Papiſtry and Hereſie ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht the confines of the Church, and Gods name praiſed and glorified both in Church and Common Wealth, ſo ſhall the Kings Honour increaſe, ſo ſhall the Parliaments Councell proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and the Subiects feare be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into ioy, ſo ſhall thoſe diſtractions ceaſe, and unity triumph in his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Dominions,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156723:4"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Die Sabbathi 28. <hi>May,</hi> 1642.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas it appeares, that the King, ſeduced by wicked Councell, intends to make Warre againſt the Parliament, and under the colour of a guard to ſecure his Royall Perſon, doth command troops of Horſe and Foote to aſſemble at <hi>Yorke;</hi> All which is againſt the Lawes of the Kingdome, tending to the diſſolution of the Parliament, and deſtruction of his People. Jt is therefore Ordered by the Lords and Commons aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Parliament, that the Sheriffs of the County of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and all other Sheriffs of the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> ſhall by the power of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of their ſeverall Counties, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, ſuppreſſe the raiſing or comming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of any Souldiers Horſe or Foote, by any Warrant, Commiſſion or Order from his Maieſty without the conſent of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and that all Perſous whatſoever
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:156723:5"/>doe forbeare to execute any ſuch Commiſſion, or warrant for levying Souldiers, or gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them together without conſent of the Parliament; And thoſe who ſhall execute, or obey any ſuch Commiſſion, or warrant, are hereby declared to be diſturbers of the peace of the Kingdome. And that his Majeſties loving Subjects may the better underſtand what the Law, and their owne duty is in this behalfe, the ſaid Sheriffe of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and other Sheriffes of the other Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Kingdome reſpectively, ſhall cauſe this preſent Order, forthwith to bee publiſhed in the ſeverall Market Towns within their ſaid Counties.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sabbathi, 28. Maii. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Ordered by the Lords in Parliament, that this ſhall be forthwith Printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Browne, Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
